Guide to the Samuel Bourne photographs, circa 1861-circa 1889 RL.00130
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Samuel Bourne photographs
circa 1861-circa 1889
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Bourne, Samuel, 1834-1912
RL.00130
21 Linear Feet 26 boxes 646 items
Collection consists of 19th century albumen photographs taken by commercial photographer Samuel Bourne and other partners as they traveled to sites in modern-day India, Bangladesh, Pakistan, and Burma. Of the 646 prints in the collection, 200 are mounted in three large bound commercial photograph albums, while the remaining 446 are single, loose prints; all were published by the firm Bourne & Shepherd. The majority of the prints range in size from roughly 6x9 to 10x12 inches. Subjects include the vast landscapes of nothern India; landmarks such as temples, rivers and canals, monuments, mountain hostels, and European-built cathedrals and civic structures; rural scenes from villages and tea plantations; and scenes from the cities of Delhi, Bombay (Mumbai), and Calcutta (Kolkata). There are also several dozen ethnic portraits of native inhabitants and group portraits of English officials and Indian counterparts. A number of images have been attributed to Bourne's partners Charles Shepherd and Colin Murray.
Collection Arrangement
All prints, whether loose or mounted in albums, are listed in the collection guide in negative number order, following the original negative number sequence on the Bourne & Shepherd studio's commercial list, which has been reconstructed by historian Hugh Rayner.
Historical Note
Samuel Bourne (1834-1912) was born in Shropshire, England, and began his career in photography around 1855. Bourne sailed for India in 1863, settling in the northern city of Shimla, which served as the launching place for the lengthy trips he took to regions of modern-day India, Pakistan, Bangladesh, and Burma. One of his trips was devoted to finding and photographing the source of the Ganges in the Himalayas. He co-founded the Bourne & Shepherd studio, which eventually had offices in Simla, Calcutta (Kolkata), and Bombay (Mumbai). Some of the images in the collection may also be the work of an earlier studio, Shepherd & Robertson, formed by Bourne's eventual partner Charles Shepherd. In 1870 Bourne returned permanently to England with his wife, Mary; Charles Shepherd also left India in 1879.
Most Bourne & Shepherd studio negative numbers above 2200 are considered the work of studio photographers following Bourne's departure in 1871. Colin Murray, in particular, seems to have been Bourne's photographic successor; Bourne gave him all of his equipment. Further, following Bourne and Shepherd's departures, Colin Murray was hired as chief photographer and then became the firm's manager.
Back in England, Bourne became a businessman and magistrate, passing away in 1912. Colin Murray died in Calcutta in 1884. The firm Bourne & Shepherd closed in 2016; up until then it was one of the oldest photography firms in the world in continuous operation. The thousands of glass plate negatives Bourne had left behind were destroyed in a fire in 1991.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Samuel Bourne photographs were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase in 2012, 2014, and 2016, and 2017.
Collection Overview
Collection consists of mid- to late 19th century albumen photographs taken by commercial photographer Samuel Bourne and other partners in the Bourne & Shepherd as they traveled to sites in modern-day India, Bangladesh, Pakistan, and Burma. Some of the early images in the collection, circa 1861, may be the work of a predecessor studio, Shepherd & Robertson. Most Bourne & Shepherd studio negative numbers after 2200 are considered the work of studio photographers following Bourne's departure in 1871; in particular, Colin Murray is considered Bourne's successor.
Of the 646 prints in the collection, 200 are mounted in three large, fine photograph albums published by the studio Bourne & Shepherd, while the remaining 446 loose prints are either loose or mounted on thin board.
Subjects in the collection include the vast landscapes of northern India; landmarks such as Hindu temples, bridges, rivers and canals, monuments, forts, mountain hostels, and European-built cathedrals and civic structures; rural scenes of villages and newly-established tea plantations; newly constructed railroads; and scenes from the cities of Delhi, Bombay (Mumbai), and Calcutta (Kolkata). Nearly every scene features a few human figures carefully posed for scale or atmosphere. Also present are a series of group portraits of English officials with their Indian counterparts, and group portraits of Indian royalty. There are also several dozen portraits of native inhabitants produced as part of the ethnic studies common to the late 19th century; most have been attributed to Bourne's partner Charles Shepherd. Many of these group studies were published in the eight-volume People of India (1868-1875), and indeed most of the portraits in this collection are on pages taken from these volumes.
The majority of the prints range in size from roughly 6x9 to 11x14 inches, with most around 10x12 inches, but a handful are smaller cartes-de-visite sizes. The images were secured in the field, often under extreme conditions, using the wet-collodion process to produce glass plate negatives, typically 10x12 inches. Some of the prints were cropped as ovals or in other shapes, but most are rectangular in form. Judging from their backings, many were previously mounted in albums or books.
Kolkata (India) -- Pictorial works; India -- Social conditions; Himalaya Mountains -- Pictorial works; India -- Social life and customs -- 19th century; India -- Pictorial works; Burma -- Pictorial works; Burma -- Social life and customs -- 19th century; Photography -- India -- History -- 19th century; Bombay (India) -- Pictorial works; Albumen prints; Documentary Photography -- India; Hindu temples -- India -- Pictorial works; Tibet Region -- Pictorial works; Nepal -- Pictorial works; Tibet Region -- Social life and customs; Photograph albums; India -- History -- British occupation, 1765-1947; Shepherd, Charles, fl. 1858-1878; Murray, Colin Roderick, 1840-1884; Bourne, Samuel, 1834-1912; Bourne & Shepherd; Archive of Documentary Arts (Duke University)
- Photographic prints, circa 1861-circa 1889; 1; 546 prints 21 boxes
  Scope and Contents
  Negative numbers and titles for the 546 images in the collection are transcribed from the original Bourne & Shepherd studio lists, which have been re-assembled in recent years by historians of photography in India. The original spellings and punctuation have been retained. Where there are gaps in those lists, the titles and numbers are taken from studio inscriptions on the negative or print, or from uncropped prints in other collections. The negative numbers, up to four digits long, have been used to create each print's unique identifier. There are some prints for which the negative numbers or titles are currently unknown; those without a known number have been given a unique identifier composed of UN and a sequential number (e.g., UN042).
  The three large brown leather and gilt albums are titled Northern India; Western, Eastern, and Southern India; and Farther India. They hold a total of 200 albumen prints, 191 of which are large-format (from 8x10 to 9x12 inches), mounted one per page; one exception is nine cartes-de-visite mounted on a single page.
  The loose single prints are either unmounted or mounted on thin stock in most cases. Typical image sizes range from 7x9 to 10x12 inches, and if the prints are mounted, they are secured to thin stock typically measuring 9x11 to 11x14 inches. Almost all the single prints are housed in modern 16x20 inch window mats.
  Many but not all of the prints in the collection are inscribed with negative numbers, short titles, and variants on the studio or photographer's name. The prints in the three albums are presented in random negative number order, but in the collection guide the entries for all the prints, loose as well as album-mounted, are listed in the same sequential negative number order as they appear in the studio's commercial list.
  Specific locations featured in the images include but are not limited to: Agra; Benares (Varanasi); Bombay (Mumbai); areas of Burma (Myanmar); Bhurtpore (Bharatpur); Calcutta (Kolkata); Darjeeling; Delhi; Futtypore Sikri (Fatehpur Sikri); Gwalior; Kashmir; Lucknow; Madura (Madurai); Mussoorie; Nepal; the Neilgherries; Ootacamund (Udagamandalam); Rangoon (Yangon, former capital of Burma); Secundra; and Simla (or Shimla). There are a handful of images featuring posed groups of high-ranking Indian officials and nobility, as well as group portraits of male and female native inhabitants, often accompanied by descriptions of their ethnic group on a leaf of text. Calcutta image #1748 features the Samuel Bourne's wife, Mary (Tolley) Bourne. Otherwise there are very few images of Europeans in the collection.
  - Simla; from Boileaugange, circa 1864; 9 1/8 x 11 3/4 inches (Box 22, Print RL-00130-P-0009)
    Original negative number: 9
    Provenance: From a presentation album of Samuel Bourne photographs dated March 26th, 1868. Unmounted.
  - Simla, from Prospect Hill, circa 1864; 9 1/8 x 11 3/4 inches (Box 22, Print RL-00130-P-0014)
    Original negative number: 14
  - Simla, from Jakko, circa 1864; 9 1/8 x 11 1/2 inches (Box 22, Print RL-00130-P-0018)
    Original negative number: 18
  - Simla; Looking Towards Jakko, 1863-1864; 8 3/4 x 10 5/8 inches (Box 4, Print RL-00130-P-0033)
    Unmounted print, cut into an oval with number cropped out. The same image in the Victoria & Albert collections is numbered 33.
    Original negative number: 33
  - The Descent from Ghoom Station to Darjeeling, 1863-1864; 8 1/2 x 11 1/4 inches (Box 15, Print RL-00130-P-0041)
    Title taken from caption on print. Location is Simla.
    Original negative number: 41
  - Simla; Jakko, south side, 1863-1864; 9 x 11 1/2 inches (Box 4, Print RL-00130-P-0047)
    Handwritten caption on mount, "Simla, Summer."
    Original negative number: 47
  - Simla; from "Oakover", 1863-1864; 9 1/4 x 11 1/2 inches (Box 15, Print RL-00130-P-0090)
    Unmounted print.
    Original negative number: 90
  - Simla; Hill Coolies with Khiltas and Dandy, 1863-1864; 9 1/8 x 11 1/4 inches (Box 14, Print RL-00130-P-0110-1)
    Original negative number: 110
  - Simla; Hill Coolies with Khiltas and Dandy, 1863-1864; 8 x 9 1/4 inches (Box 15, Print RL-00130-P-0110-2)
  - Simla; Group of Thugs, circa 1861; 8 5/8 x 10 7/8 inches (Box 1, Print RL-00130-P-0128)
    From Photograph Album 1: Farther India, page 39. This image has been attributed to the work of Charles Shepherd for the firm of Shepherd and Robertson, which preceded Bourne & Shepherd.
    Original negative number: 128
  - Simla, circa 1864; 9 1/4 x 11 1/2 inches (Box 22, Print RL-00130-P-0129)
    Original negative number: 129
  - The Sutlej; junction of the Buspa, 1863-1864; 8 3/4 x 9 1/2 inches (Box 4, Print RL-00130-P-0181)
    Unmounted print. Number handwritten on back of print.
    Original negative number: 181
  - The Sutlej; above Barung, 1863-1864; 9 1/8 x 10 3/4 inches (Box 14, Print RL-00130-P-0184)
    Original negative number: 184
  - View from Rogi, near Chini, 1863-1864; 9 3/8 x 11 1/2 inches (Box 14, Print RL-00130-P-0202)
    Original negative number: 202
  - View in the Wanga Valley, 1863-1864; 11 1/4 x 9 1/8 inches (Box 4, Print RL-00130-P-0261)
    Plate 65 of "India Through the Lens" written on print mount.
    Original negative number: 261
  - Junction of the Wanga and Sutlej rivers, 1863-1864; 11 1/2 x 9 1/2 inches (Box 15, Print RL-00130-P-0268)
    Original negative number: 268
  - View near Tarunda, 1863-1864; 9 1/4 x 11 1/2 inches (Box 15, Print RL-00130-P-0278)
    Original negative number: 278
  - The Wanga Valley, circa 1863; 9 1/2 x 11 1/2 inches (Box 15, Print RL-00130-P-0279)
    Noted on Bourne & Shepherd studio list: "Prize photograph, 1863-64."
    Original negative number: 279
  - General View of the Wanga Valley, 1863-1864; 9 1/2 x 11 1/2 inches (Box 15, Print RL-00130-P-0282)
    Original negative number: 282
  - The Wanga Valley, 1863; 10 3/8 x 8 1/2 inches (Box 26, Print RL-00130-P-0292)
    Original negative number: 292
    Unsigned and unnumbered. Negative number assigned by dealer from unknown source; title taken from reconstructed studio catalog. Mounted on board.
  - Sir Hugh Rose's Bungalow, Mahasoo, 1863-1864; 9 x 11 1/4 inches (Box 4, Print RL-00130-P-0301)
    Original negative number: 301
  - Lucknow, La Martiniere College, circa 1861-1863; 9 3/4 x 14 1/2 inches (Box 14, Print RL-00130-P-0322)
    Attributed to Shepherd and Robertson.
    Original negative number: 322
  - Lucknow; Entrance to the Secundra Bagh, circa 1861-1863; 10 1/4 x 15 1/2 inches (Box 14, Print RL-00130-P-0324)
    Shepherd and Robertson.
    Original negative number: 324
  - Lucknow; The Bailey Guard Gate, circa 1862; 10 7/8 x 14 3/8 inches (Box 26, Print RL-00130-P-0341)
    Original negative number: 341
    Title from hand-lettered caption on mount. Signed "Shepherd & Robertson 341." Mounted on board or leaf from album. Probably by Charles Shepherd, who was with the firm of Shepherd & Robertson (in Agra) before joining Bourne in his studio.
  - Delhi; Remains of Hindu Architecture near the Kutub, Colonnade of the Temple or Bhoot-Khana of Pirthwi Rajah, circa 1862; 11 x 14 1/2 inches (Box 26, Print RL-00130-P-0378)
    Original negative number: 378
    Unsigned; negative number present on print. Mounted on large board. Dealer's note on back of mat attributes this image also to Shepherd & Robertson and gives a date of 1862.
  - Agra; The Mausoleum of Prince Etmad-Dowlah, 1863-1864; 10 3/4 x 14 1/4 inches (Box 12, Print RL-00130-P-0389)
    Original negative number: 389
  - Amritsar; The Golden Temple, 1863-1864; 8 x 11 3/8 inches (Box 2, Print RL-00130-P-0407)
    From Photograph Album 2: Northern India, page 65.
    Original negative number: 407
  - Amritsar; The Habitual Tower beside the Sacred Tank, 1863-1864; 8 x 10 3/4 inches (Box 15, Print RL-00130-P-0409)
    Dealer-assigned title, unrecorded source.
    Original negative number: 409
  - Amritsar; The Babtul Temple, Flying Foxes in Tree, 1863-1864; 9 x 11 1/2 inches (Box 2, Print RL-00130-P-0410)
    From Photograph Album 2: Northern India, page 64.
    Original negative number: 410
  - Lahore; View from Palace in the Fort, 1863-1864; 9 1/4 x 11 5/8 inches (Box 2, Print RL-00130-P-0416)
    From Photograph Album 2: Northern India, page 63.
    Original negative number: 416
  - No known title, 1863-1864; 9 1/4 x 11 5/8 inches (Box 2, Print RL-00130-P-0417)
    From Photograph Album 2: Northern India, page 62. Uncaptioned print; title not present on current Bourne & Shepherd studio list. Studio title of 418 is "Lahore; Ranjit Singh's Tomb," showing the same subject as this print.
    Original negative number: 417
  - Lahore; Jahangir's Tomb, in the Shadra Gardens, 1863-1864; 9 3/8 x 11 5/8 inches (Box 2, Print RL-00130-P-0424)
    From Photograph Album 2: Northern India, page 61.
    Original negative number: 424
  - Lahore; Sir Robert Montgomery's Camel Carriages, Government House, 1863-1864; 9 1/8 x 11 5/8 inches (Box 1, Print RL-00130-P-0426)
    From Photograph Album 1: Farther India, page 38. Studio number not present on print; verified through studio list and captioned prints in other collections.
    Original negative number: 426
  - Simla; Jakko, showing the Club, circa 1863; 9 1/8 x 11 1/2 inches (Box 22, Print RL-00130-P-0438)
    Original negative number: 438
  - Dhurmsala; The Church through the Trees, 1863-1864; 4 x 3 3/4 inches (Box 4, Print RL-00130-P-0457)
    Original negative number: 457
  - Kangra; The Village of Negrota, 1863-1864; 4 1/4 x 7 5/8 inches (Box 4, Print RL-00130-P-0479)
    Original negative number: 479
  - Government Tea Plantation, Holta, 1863-1864; 4 x 7 5/8 inches (Box 4, Print RL-00130-P-0481)
    Unmounted print (detached from a board at some point). Number written on back of print.
    Original negative number: 481
  - Kangra; Bridge and Fort, circa 1864; 9 1/8 x 11 3/8 inches (Box 22, Print RL-00130-P-0505)
    Original negative number: 505
  - Kangra; Monuments of Sutteeism, 1863-1864; 9 1/2 x 11 1/2 inches (Box 15, Print RL-00130-P-0511)
    Original negative number: 511
  - Kangra; Golden Temple, circa 1864; 9 1/4 x 11 1/4 inches (Box 22, Print RL-00130-P-0512)
    Original negative number: 512
    Provenance: From a presentation album of Samuel Bourne photographs dated March 26th, 1868. Unmounted. Image of narrow street, lined with shops and people, leading downwards to the domed temple.
  - Cascade, Kangra Valley, circa 1864; 10 5/8 x 9 1/2 inches (Box 22, Print RL-00130-P-0517)
    Original negative number: 517
    Provenance: From a presentation album of Samuel Bourne photographs dated March 26th, 1868. Title from unknown source; not found on currently known studio catalog. Unmounted.
  - Dhurmsala; The Church from the South-West, circa 1864; 9 3/8 x 11 3/8 inches (Box 22, Print RL-00130-P-0520)
    Original negative number: 520
  - Dhurmsala; Panorama from the Rajah of Kaputhulla's House, part 1, circa 1864; 9 3/8 x 11 3/8 inches (Box 22, Print RL-00130-P-0521)
    Original negative number: 521
  - Dhurmsala; Panorama from the Rajah of Kaputhulla's House, part 2, circa 1864; 9 3/8 x 11 3/8 inches (Box 22, Print RL-00130-P-0522)
    Original negative number: 522
  - Dhurmsala; From the Barracks, 1863-1864; 9 1/4 x 11 1/2 inches (Box 4, Print RL-00130-P-0523)
    Original negative number: 523
  - Dhurmsala; Panoramic view from the Barracks, part 1, circa 1864; 9 1/8 x 11 1/4 inches (Box 22, Print RL-00130-P-0528)
    Original negative number: 528
  - Dhurmsala; Panoramic view from the Barracks, part 2, circa 1864; 9 1/8 x 11 1/8 inches (Box 22, Print RL-00130-P-0529)
    Original negative number: 529
    Provenance: From a presentation album of Samuel Bourne photographs dated March 26th, 1868. Unmounted. Print exhibits crazing from original negative plate emulsion.
  - Dhurmsala; Panoramic view from the Barracks, part 3, circa 1864; 9 1/4 x 11 1/8 inches (Box 22, Print RL-00130-P-0530)
    Original negative number: 530
  - View at Karare, 1863-1864; 9 1/2 x 11 1/2 inches (Box 15, Print RL-00130-P-0531)
    Original negative number: 531
  - View on the Kholee at Rhotee, 1863-1864; 9 1/2 x 11 1/2 inches (Box 4, Print RL-00130-P-0533)
    Original negative number: 533
  - The Balayn Pass into the Valley of the Ravee, circa 1864; 9 1/2 x 11 3/8 inches (Box 22, Print RL-00130-P-0534)
    Original negative number: 534
  - Dalhousie; from the Mall looking towards Hotel, circa 1864; 9 3/8 x 11 1/4 inches (Box 22, Print RL-00130-P-0539)
    Original negative number: 539
  - Dalhousie; Perasona, from Putrain Hill, circa 1866; 9 1/4 x 11 1/4 inches (Box 22, Print RL-00130-P-0541)
    Original negative number: 541
  - Chamba; View on the Ravee, circa 1864; 9 1/2 x 11 1/2 inches (Box 15, Print RL-00130-P-0550)
    Original negative number: 550
  - Chamba; from Choughan or Hockey Ground, circa 1863; 9 1/4 x 11 1/8 inches (Box 22, Print RL-00130-P-0551)
    Original negative number: 551
  - Chamba Valley, circa 1864; 9 3/8 x 11 3/8 inches (Box 4, Print RL-00130-P-0552)
    Original negative number: 552
  - Chamba; A Group of Guddies, circa 1864; 8 7/8 x 11 1/8 inches (Box 1, Print RL-00130-P-0554)
    From Photograph Album 1: Farther India, page 40.
    Original negative number: 554
  - A Nautch at Shalimar, circa 1864; 8 7/8 x 11 1/8 inches (Box 1, Print RL-00130-P-0606)
    From Photograph Album 1: Farther India, page 43. Shows a dance at a famous garden in Srinagar.
    Original negative number: 606
  - Poplar Avenue at Islamabad, circa 1864; 4 1/8 x 3 3/4 inches (Box 4, Print RL-00130-P-0637)
    Original negative number: 637
  - Srinuggur; View down the Jhelum from the Island, circa 1864-1865; 4 1/8 x 3 3/4 inches (Box 4, Print RL-00130-P-0644)
    Once attached to a mount; some material still adheres to print.
    Original negative number: 644
  - View from Kishtwar, circa 1864-1865; 4 1/8 x 7 1/4 inches (Box 4, Print RL-00130-P-0697)
    Original negative number: 697
  - Panorama of Islamabad from Hill Above, part 1, circa 1864-1865; 4 1/8 x 7 1/2 inches (Box 4, Print RL-00130-P-0718)
    Original negative number: 718
  - View on the Kashmir Road, Near Budrawar, circa 1864-1865; 8 5/8 x 11 1/4 inches (Box 4, Print RL-00130-P-0774)
    Original negative number: 774
  - Twig Jhula bridge on the Chenab, Near Kishtowar, circa 1864-1865; 9 x 11 1/4 inches (Box 4, Print RL-00130-P-0776)
    Original negative number: 776
  - Large Chunars, by the Stream, at Achabul, circa 1864; 9 1/2 x 11 1/2 inches (Box 22, Print RL-00130-P-0780)
    Original negative number: 780
  - Ruins of Martund, from the North-East, circa 1865; 9 x 11 inches (Box 22, Print RL-00130-P-0781)
    Original negative number: 781
  - Bij Bihara, on the Jhelum, circa 1864; 9 1/8 x 10 5/8 inches (Box 22, Print RL-00130-P-0784)
    Original negative number: 784
    Provenance: From a presentation album of Samuel Bourne photographs dated March 26th, 1868. Bijbehara is an ancient village on the Jhelum River, Kashmir Valley. Unmounted.
  - View at Bij Bihara, down the Jhelum, from the island, circa 1864; 9 1/2 x 11 1/8 inches (Box 22, Print RL-00130-P-0786)
    Original negative number: 786
  - View at Bij Bihara, from above the Char Chunar, circa 1864; 9 3/8 x 11 1/2 inches (Box 22, Print RL-00130-P-0787)
    Original negative number: 787
  - Srinuggur; Bridge of Shops, circa 1864-1865; 8 1/2 x 11 1/2 inches (Box 14, Print RL-00130-P-0788-1)
    Original negative number: 788
  - Srinuggur; Bridge of Shops, circa 1864-1865; 9 1/4 x 11 1/2 inches (Box 15, Print RL-00130-P-0788-2)
  - Srinuggur; Shah Hamadan Musjid, circa 1864-1865; 8 1/2 x 11 1/2 inches (Box 14, Print RL-00130-P-0789)
    Original negative number: 789
  - Srinuggur; Moonshee Bagh: Commissioner's Boat, circa 1864; 9 1/4 x 11 3/8 inches (Box 22, Print RL-00130-P-0790)
    Original negative number: 790
    Provenance: From a presentation album of Samuel Bourne photographs dated March 26th, 1868. Srinagar is a city on the Jhelum River, in the Kashmir Valley. Unmounted.
  - Srinuggur; Visitor's reach, circa 1864; 9 1/4 x 11 1/8 inches (Box 22, Print RL-00130-P-0793)
    Original negative number: 793
  - Srinuggur; View down the River, from the 3rd Bridge, circa 1864-1865; 9 1/8 x 11 1/4 inches (Box 4, Print RL-00130-P-0795)
    Unmounted print; some damage to negative has conveyed to print.
    Original negative number: 795
  - Srinuggur; On the Dhal Canal, 1st reach from city, circa 1864-1865; 9 1/4 x 11 5/8 inches (Box 14, Print RL-00130-P-0796)
    Original negative number: 796
  - Srinuggur; On the Dhul Canal, near the City, circa 1864-1865; 9 1/8 x 11 1/2 inches (Box 26, Print RL-00130-P-0797)
    Original negative number: 797
    Mounted on board.
  - Srinuggur; On the Dhul Canal, with the Tukt-i-Soliman, circa 1864; 9 1/4 x 11 3/8 inches (Box 22, Print RL-00130-P-0798)
    Original negative number: 798
  - Srinuggur; Showing how the Vines grow in Kashmir, circa 1864-1865; 11 1/4 x 9 3/8 inches (Box 14, Print RL-00130-P-0799-1)
    Original negative number: 799
  - Srinuggur; Showing how the Vines grow in Kashmir, circa 1864-1865; 9 1/4 x 11 3/4 inches (Box 15, Print RL-00130-P-0799-2)
  - Srinuggur - Avenue of Vines and Poplars, circa 1864; 10 1/8 x 9 3/8 inches (Box 22, Print RL-00130-P-0800)
    Original negative number: 800
  - Srinuggur; Poplar Avenue, from the end, circa 1864-1865; 11 1/2 x 9 1/2 inches (Box 15, Print RL-00130-P-0801)
    Original negative number: 801